A Guide to the John Malcus Ellison Papers 1941-1979
Archives and Special Collections Department, L. Douglas Wilder Library, Virginia Union University
Archives and Special Collections Department, L. Douglas Wilder Library, Virginia Union University
John Malcus Ellison Papers 1941-1979
Archives and Special Collections Department, L. Douglas Wilder Library, Virginia Union University
MS-0001
12 linear feet
John Malcus Ellison Papers
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Received from Elizabeth Balfour Ellison, 06 August 1993
Biographical/Historical Information
Born 02 February 1889 in Northumberland County, Virginia, John Malcus Ellison was one of twin sons. His early life was very humble allowing for very little intellectual stimulation beyond learning to read in the racially segregated schools of his rural community. As he explained in a short autobiographical sketch he wrote to James H. Croushore of Fredricksburg, Virginia in the late 1950's, At the age of 14 I was hired out for 7.00 dollars per month as a farm hand. My varied experiences caused me much unrest and anxiety as I longed for a fuller and more meaningful life Opportunities for education were very meager in my home community, and so at the age of 17 I went to Normal Industrial Institute now Virginia State College at Petersburg, Va. After two and one half years of study I transferred to Virginia Union University in 1909 and completed my High School and College work. At that time, Wayland Academy was the division of Union that provided secondary education to students. In 1917, Ellison earned his A.B. in Education at Virginia Union. He returned to his home in the Northern Neck of Virginia as pastor of Shiloh Baptist Church and principal of the Northern Neck Industrial Academy. He later founded and headed the Northumberland County High School.
In 1927 Ellison earned a Master of Arts in Religious Education and Philosophy of Religion from Oberlin College and subsequently taught at what is now Virginia State University in sociology and ethics. There he was appointed the first college minister. He did graduate work at Columbia University from 1930 to 1931 and at Union Theological Seminary in New York City from 1931 to 1932. By 1933, Ellison had earned his Ph.D. in Christian Education and Sociology from Drew University, been pastor of the Zion Baptist Church in Washington, D.C., taught Religious Education at Howard University's School of Religion, and authored several publications on rural, Negro life in Virginia. It was in that same year that he married Elizabeth Balfour, a music educator and performer from Brooklyn, New York.
Dr. Ellison assumed the presidency of Virginia Union at a very difficult time in history. The country had just entered World War II and the era of Jim Crow was at its peak in the South. Being the first African American to assume the leadership of Virginia Union, he lived with the burden of proving himself capable and worthy of the title President. It is generally believed that he succeeded at the task. In spite of the manpower drain on both the student body and the male faculty, Union survived the worst of times through 1946 when the GIs returned to school and prosperity and stability came back to the university. Ellison took an active part in the support of US troops, especially Virginia Union students in the service, and in the civilian efforts that maintained the community at home. It was also during his administration that the Belgian Friendship Building project was undertaken and successfully accomplished.
After the 1939 World's Fair in New York City, the Belgian government could not dismantle and return their elaborate exhibit and its housing to Nazi-occupied Belgium. Several options were explored to dispose of the splendid structure originally designed to be a stand-alone college in Belgium. Benefactors of Negro education, however, won the bid. The Belgian Friendship Building with its ornate friezes depicting black life in the Belgian Congo would be relocated to the campus of Virginia Union University. Negotiations for the transfer of title and property were begun in the previous administration of William J. Clark; fund raising, re-design and physical relocation were left to Ellison's stewardship. By 1949 the campus had been renovated, the Belgian building moved and fitted for the library, science laboratories and the gymnasium and a debt of nearly one-half million dollars had been retired under Ellison's leadership. This project was a major concern during the first half of his career and his papers reflect its importance.
Other improvements on the campus followed the Belgian Building project including re-organization of the university's administrative structure, significant increase in the endowment, and additions to the physical plant (e.g., Hovey Stadium, new dormitories and other facilities).
Concurrent with his academic and administrative career, Ellison kept an active ministerial career, preaching and teaching throughout Virginia on a regular basis and appearing as guest pastor a various churches, Sunday Schools and conferences all over the country. Summers were often spent teaching aspiring ministers in special programs that he helped design. He edited religious journals and newsletters as well as publications for the Scottish Rite and Alpha Phi Alpha Fraternity, Inc. Ellison was a prolific author as well; he published several books, tracts and brochures most of which were copies of his favorite and most popular sermons.
As a prominent African American educator, Ellison was active in many organizations advancing the cause of both civil rights and higher education for his race. His involvement with national organizations such as the National Youth Administration, Southern Education Foundation, Negro Organization Society, National Conference of Church-Related Colleges, the NAACP and many others was typical of African American leaders of that time as they cooperated to support the existence and survival of their schools and institutions.
After his term as president, Ellison continued on at Virginia Union as chancellor and professor until his death on 13 October 1979. He is buried at Riverview Cemetery in Richmond, Virginia.
Scope and Content Information
This collection contains the administrative and personal records of John Malcus Ellison as president of Virginia Union University (1941-1955), chancellor (1955-79), minister, teacher, author and editor. The bulk of the collection is from the early years of his presidency, 1941-1945, with very few materials from the later years or during his tenure as chancellor. Although most of the collection is correspondence conducted in his official capacity as president, because these materials were received from his family, the Ellison Papers are organized as a manuscript collection.
The correspondence files give an intriguing picture of Ellison in his role as president of a small, African American university in a segregated southern city. The many letters from parents, guardians and prospective students reflect his function as father and disciplinarian to the campus. The letters to and from prominent Richmond figures and leaders of the area schools, both black and white, reveal the part he played in community relations. Of special interest is the correspondence with other African American educational leaders, such as Benjamin Mays, which shows the support these educators lent one another in their struggles for their institutions to not only survive, but succeed.
The subject files disclose what organizations Ellison participated in as president. Like many of his contemporaries, he was active in national organizations as they provided a support network for African American higher education. These files also reveal what was happening on campus during the early years of his administration, including the Belgian Building files which offer a fascinating unfolding of the construction of the building.
The personal files are related mainly to his role as preacher and teacher. As with the other series, the lines are often blurred in these files between Ellison's many roles. His speeches and sermons are an interesting compliment to his writings, and often there is overlap between the two as he published collections of sermons. Included in the writings are his extensive notes in preparation for a definitive history of Virginia Union, for which many of the photographs in these materials were collected. The programs show not only which events and activities Ellison participated in, both on campus and off, but those which he attended or supported.
Due to severe mold damage and insect infestation, many records have been preservation photocopied.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged by series and chronological therein.
Contents List
- Series 1. Correspondence 1941-1978, 2500 items
  The correspondence spans Ellison's Virginia Union career from 1941 almost until his death in 1979. It is primarily routine correspondence between Ellison and financial contributors, student and job applicants, foundation officers, organizational representatives, alumni and parents. Much of Ellison's correspondence was directed to donors, large and small, especially while fundraising for the Belgian Building.
  Personnel issues, as well as student discipline, are included throughout all of the correspondence. The advent of exchange student enrollment from Africa and the Caribbean is reflected as well. Dr. and Mrs. Ellison were described as having this mission: bringing foreign students to Virginia Union for their post-secondary education. There are social notes as well as letters of introduction, reference and inquiry from and about several such students.
  Several letters of interest from prospective teachers provide profiles of aspiring African American professionals during the Jim Crow era. Missives from parents and guardians about their young people away at school for the first time reflect the more comprehensive, paternal role of the African American college administrator of the time. Threads of dialogue between Ellison and concerned fathers can be traced in the correspondence concerning the progress of Simeon Booker, Jr., Adam Clayton Powell, Jr., and William H. Gray, Jr. as examples.
  Newly appointed presidents and principals of black institutions were his contemporaries; as a network of leaders, they corresponded frequently both professionally and personally about issues facing African Americans at that time. The success or failure of the schools originally founded to educate and uplift the emancipated slaves depended upon their leadership and tenacity. Both male and female administrators were active in this support network as evidenced by correspondence from Nannie Burroughs, Mary McLeod Bethune, and Charlotte Hawkins Brown along with Benjamin Mays, Mordecai Johnson, F. D. Bluford, and Miles W. Connor, all prominent leaders of black educational institutions. Other notable personages among the correspondents are Rev. Vernon Johns, Carter G. Woodson, and Judge William H. Hastie.
  chronological
  - January-June 1941 (Box-folder 1.1)
  - July 1941 (Box-folder 1.2)
  - August 1941 (Box-folder 1.3)
  - September 1941 (Box-folder 1.4)
  - October 1941 (Box-folder 1.5)
  - November 1941 (Box-folder 1.6)
  - December 1941 (Box-folder 1.7)
  - January 1942 (Box-folder 1.8)
  - February 1942 (Box-folder 1.9)
  - March 1942 (Box-folder 1.10)
  - April 1942 (Box-folder 1.11)
  - May 1942 (Box-folder 1.12)
  - June 1942 (Box-folder 1.13)
  - July 1942 (Box-folder 1.14)
  - August 1942 (Box-folder 1.15)
  - September 1942 (Box-folder 1.16)
  - October 1942 (Box-folder 1.17)
  - November 1942 (Box-folder 1.18)
  - December 1942 (Box-folder 1.19)
  - January 1943 (Box-folder 1.20)
  - February 1943 (Box-folder 1.21)
  - March 1943 (Box-folder 1.22)
  - April 1943 (Box-folder 1.23)
  - May 1943 (Box-folder 1.24)
  - June 1943 (Box-folder 2.25)
  - July 1943 (Box-folder 2.26)
  - August 1943 (Box-folder 2.27)
  - September 1943 (Box-folder 2.28)
  - October 1943 (Box-folder 2.29)
  - November 1943 (Box-folder 2.30)
  - December 1943 (Box-folder 2.31)
  - January 1944 (Box-folder 2.32)
  - February 1944 (Box-folder 2.33)
  - March 1944 (Box-folder 2.34)
  - April 1944 (Box-folder 2.35)
  - May 1944 (Box-folder 2.36)
  - June 1944 (Box-folder 2.37)
  - July 1944 (Box-folder 2.38)
  - August 1944 (Box-folder 2.39)
  - September 1944 (Box-folder 2.40)
  - October 1944 (Box-folder 2.41)
  - November 1944 (Box-folder 2.42)
  - December 1944 (Box-folder 2.43)
  - January 1945 (Box-folder 2.44)
  - February-March 1945 (Box-folder 2.45)
  - April-May 1945 (Box-folder 2.46)
  - June-July 1945 (Box-folder 2.47)
  - August-December 1945 (Box-folder 2.48)
  - Correspondence 1946 (Box-folder 3.49)
  - Correspondence 1947 (Box-folder 3.50)
  - Correspondence 1948-1949 (Box-folder 3.51)
  - Correspondence 1950-1951 (Box-folder 3.52)
  - January-August 1952 (Box-folder 3.53)
  - September-October 1952 (Box-folder 3.54)
  - November-December 1952 (Box-folder 3.55)
  - January-February 1953 (Box-folder 3.56)
  - March-April 1953 (Box-folder 3.57)
  - May 1953 (Box-folder 3.58)
  - June 1953 (Box-folder 3.59)
  - July 1953 (Box-folder 3.60)
  - August-September 1953 (Box-folder 3.61)
  - Correspondence 1954-1955 (Box-folder 3.62)
  - Correspondence 1956-1959 (Box-folder 3.63)
  - Correspondence 1961-1978 (Box-folder 3.64)
- Series 2. Special Correspondence 1941-1947, 500 items
  Ellison kept separate files for certain individuals who were primarily fundraisers first pressed into service for the Belgian Building project. Some worked among African American friends and churches and others were institutional representatives who handled larger sums of money. In the case of Marie Hancock (Mrs. Gordon), she was apparently an employed fund developer for the university, while Miles Connor and C. L. Franklin were active alumni chapter presidents. Because of the distinction of being the first African American president of Virginia Union, Ellison received many pieces of congratulatory correspondence ranging from commercial greeting cards to letters and telegrams. The latter were preservation photocopied.
  - Congratulatory Letters (Box-folder 3.65)
  - Connor, Miles W. (Box-folder 3.66)
  - Foster, Luther H. (Box-folder 3.67)
  - Franklin, C. L. (Box-folder 3.68)
  - Hancock, Marie (Box-folder 3.69)
  - Norris, Morgan E. (Box-folder 3.70)
  - Porter, Henry A. (Box-folder 3.71)
  - Powell, Adam Clayton, Sr. (Box-folder 3.72)
- Series 3. Subject Files 1939-1970, 2000 items
  Ellison's role as college administrator meant that he was involved in every facet of campus business, as well as with many civic, state and national organizations. These subject files demonstrate the multiple hats Ellison wore as president of Virginia Union. Materials such as those in the administrative, Athletics Department and Library files reveal that he was active in the day-to-day business of the campus departments. It was this same intimate involvement that made him so active in personnel and student affairs as exemplified in the application and recommendation letters. (Job applicants often included photographs with their resumes. These snapshots have been removed and housed in PMS-001.)
  A definite portrait of the times in which Ellison was working can also be found in the subject files. In files regarding wartime matters, there is material about life during World War II and the Negro's role and expectations during and after it. The many organizations dealing with race relations belie the tense days as institutionalized segregation was coming to an end. The files for educational organizations show the support available at that time to the president of a small African American university.
  alphabetical then chronological
  - Administrative 1940-1944 (Box-folder 4.73)
  - Administrative 1945-1949 (Box-folder 4.74)
  - Administrative 1950-1979 (Box-folder 4.75)
  - Africa Committee (Box-folder 4.76)
  - Alumni Association (VUU) (Box-folder 4.77)
  - American Council on Education (Box-folder 4.78)
  - American Teachers Association (Box-folder 4.79)
  - Application Letters 1941-1943 (Box-folder 4.80)
  - Application Letters 1944-1945 (Box-folder 4.81)
  - Photographs (removed to PMS-0001) (Box-folder 4.82)
  - Association of American Colleges (Box-folder 4.83)
  - Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools for Negroes (Box-folder 4.84)
  - Central Intercollegiate Athletic Association (Box-folder 4.85)
  - Correspondence 1939-1941 (Box-folder 4.86)
  - Correspondence 1942 (Box-folder 4.87)
  - Correspondence 1943-1947 (Box-folder 4.88)
  - Financial Records (Box-folder 4.89)
  - National Collegiate Athletic Association (Box-folder 4.90)
  - Programs (Box-folder 4.91)
  - Public Relations (Box-folder 4.92)
  - Baptist Board of Education (Box-folder 4.93)
  - Barco, John W. (Box-folder 4.94)
  - Belgian Building (Box-folder 4.95)
  - Hening, S.E. (Box-folder 4.96)
  - Publications (Box-folder 4.97)
  - Van Kuyck, Hugo (Box-folder 4.98)
  - Budget (Box-folder 4.99)
  - Commencement 1941-1942 (Box-folder 4.100)
  - Commission on Interracial Cooperation, Inc. (Box-folder 4.101)
  - Faculty Committee Reports (Box-folder 5.102)
  - Faculty Meeting Minutes (Box-folder 5.103)
  - Fetter, Newton C. (Box-folder 5.104)
  - Founder's Day Letters (Box-folder 5.105)
  - Hampton Institute (Box-folder 5.106)
  - Haynes, George E. (Box-folder 5.107)
  - Administrative (Box-folder 5.108)
  - Calendars and Schedules (Box-folder 5.109)
  - Correspondence (Box-folder 5.110)
  - Howard University, Washington, D.C. (Box-folder 5.111)
  - Julius Rosenwald Fund (Box-folder 5.112)
  - Lee, J. Oscar (Box-folder 5.113)
  - Annual Reports and Miscellaneous (Box-folder 5.114)
  - Correspondence 1941-1942 (Box-folder 5.115)
  - Correspondence 1943-1950 (Box-folder 5.116)
  - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 5.117)
  - National Association of Collegiate Deans and Registrars in Negro Schools (Box-folder 5.118)
  - National Conference of Church-Related Colleges (Box-folder 5.119)
  - National Education Association (Box-folder 5.120)
  - National Student Health Association (Box-folder 1.21)
  - National Urban League (Box-folder 5.122)
  - National Youth Administration (Box-folder 5.123)
  - Negro Organization Society (Box-folder 5.124)
  - Public Relations (Box-folder 5.125)
  - Rationing Board (Box-folder 5.126)
  - Recommendations 1941-1942 (Box-folder 5.127)
  - Recommendations 1943-1945 (Box-folder 5.128)
  - Richmond Community Council (Box-folder 5.129)
  - Scholarships (Box-folder 5.130)
  - Southern Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools (Box-folder 5.131)
  - Southern Conference on Race Relations (Box-folder 5.132)
  - Southern Education Foundation 1941-1947 (Box-folder 5.133)
  - Southern Education Foundation 1948-1961 (Box-folder 5.133)
  - State Board of Education (Box-folder 5.135)
  - Student Government Association (Box-folder 5.136)
  - U.S. Office of Education (Box-folder 5.137)
  - Veterans Administration (Box-folder 5.138)
  - Virginia Conference on Race Relations (Box-folder 5.139)
  - Virginia Council of Churches, Department of Interracial Cooperation (Box-folder 5.140)
  - Virginia State Teachers Association (Box-folder 5.141)
  - World War II Materials (Box-folder 5.142)
  - YMCA (Box-folder 5.143)
- Series 4. Personal Files 1941-1978, About 1200 items
  Ellison led active life off campus as well. He kept an active preaching schedule both locally and across the country. (Frequently, when visiting a distant city on Union business, Reverend and Mrs. Ellison would appear as guest preacher and soloist to help offset the expenses of travel.) He was president of the Richmond Ministers Association and the National Program for the Training of Negro Ministers. He was also a member of Alpha Phi Alpha and the Masons (United Supreme Council).
  His speeches and sermons grouped here are typed, often untitled essays which seem to be written as orations. There may be some overlap with his writings, especially since most of his publications were originally conceived and presented as sermons.
  Ellison was editor of the Baptist Herald (Richmond, Va) and the Scottish Rite Informer (Southern Jurisdiction), and many of his articles and editorials are in the collection. Articles submitted to the periodicals under his supervision are also included, but not always identified with their authors.
  - Baptist Herald (Box-folder 6.144)
  - Baptist Training Union Lessons (Box-folder 6.145)
  - Biographies (VUU) (Box-folder 6.146)
  - Clippings (Box-folder 6.147)
  - Connor, Miles W. (Clippings) (Box-folder 6.148)
  - Correspondence and Miscellaneous (Box-folder 6.149)
  - Inaugural Addresses and Eulogies (Box-folder 6.150)
  - Ministerial Materials (Box-folder 6.151)
  - Practice Preaching (Box-folder 6.152)
  - Richmond Ministers Association (Box-folder 6.153)
  - Scottish Rite (Box-folder 6.154)
  - Social Christianity (Seminary Notes at Alderson-Broadus) (Box-folder 6.155)
  - Speeches and Sermons (Box-folder 6.156)
  - Speeches and Sermons (Box-folder 6.157)
  - Speeches and Sermons (Box-folder 6.158)
  - Teaching Materials (Box-folder 6..159)
  - Syllabi and Course Outlines (Box-folder 6.160)
  - Syllabus- Literature in the Ministry of Preaching (Box-folder 6.161)
- Series 5. Writings 1945-1978, About 2000 items
  Ellison wrote several books and religious pamphlets based on his sermons. He also in the years after his presidency, was working on a history of Virginia Union. His drafts and research notes are included here. Most of his books, including his reports written as a sociologist, are available in the library's rare books collection
  alphabetical
  - Subseries 5.1. General Writings, 1000 items
    The smaller books and tracts are filed here, some with the original manuscript. The miscellaneous files are partial writings or those that were not published. The correspondence is between Ellison and his publishers regarding his writings.
    - Correspondence (Box-folder 6.162)
    - The Abiding Influence of a Faithful Minister (Box-folder 6.163)
    - Achieving Character Through Christian Education (Box-folder 6.164)
    - The Christian Minister and His Preparation (Box-folder 6.165)
    - The Church Associations-Their Program and Task (Box-folder 6.166)
    - The Church of Our Times and Her Inescapable Challenges (Box-folder 6.167)
    - The Church's Program in Times of War (Box-folder 6.168)
    - Finding Life's Adequate Mastery (Box-folder 6.169)
    - His Disciple Came Unto Him (Box-folder 6.170)
    - How God Made His Prophets (Box-folder 6.171)
    - Let This Mind Be In You (Box-folder 6.172)
    - Life's Adventures (Box-folder 6.173)
    - The Minister: His Educational Leadership and Message (Box-folder 6.174)
    - The More Excellent Way (Box-folder 6.175)
    - The Personal Quality in Preaching and the Preacher's Message from the Psalms (Box-folder 6.176)
    - Prayers and Meditation Expressions (Box-folder 6.177)
    - The Preacher: His Preparation and Message (Box-folder 6.178)
    - Preparing to Preach in the Space Age and The Master's Method: The Preacher's Supreme Example (Box-folder 6.180)
    - Tension and Destiny (Box-folder 6.181)
    - They Who Preach (Box-folder 6.182)
    - A Trilogy on Adventurous Living (Box-folder 6.183)
    - The Voice of Music in Human Experience and the Great Organ (Box-folder 6.184)
    - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 7.185)
    - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 7.186)
  - Subseries 5.2. History of Virginia Union University, 1000 items